Your health insurance policy
is cashless.  very good thing.  But one question
always remains in your mind that if tomorrow
you yourself fall ill, will your
family be able to use the cashless process?
Because they don't have any information.  So today
's video is going to be very useful for you and your family.
Because in this we have
completely simplified the cashless process.  It has been made easy
to understand.
So before discussing the cashless process,
I would like to give you two clarities.
First of all, the clarity is that no matter which
company's policy you are running, be it HDFC,
ICICI, LB, Niva, BPA, CK, Halth, Bajaj, Alan or
any government company's policy, every company
offers you both cashless and reimbursement facilities within the policy.  So if for some
reason your claim is not cashless
then you can also file for reimbursement.
Both facilities are provided within the policy.  The
second clarity is
that the cashless process is the
same in every hospital.  Whether you
go to Face Hospital, Chahengaram,
Max, Medta or
any other small or big hospital.
This process will be the same everywhere and
you will have to follow the same steps.  So, this
entire cashless process has been
divided into a total of six steps.  So let
me tell you six steps one by one what
you have to do.
Step number one of the cashless process is to
identify the hospital.  In which hospital will we get
our patient treated?
For this we will have to visit the company's website
or use the company's mobile app.
Where
we can check the list of the company's network cashless hospitals.
If our hospital is in the list then
we will get cashless treatment and if
by chance our hospital is not in that list then
we will have to make the claim for reimbursement.
If we are getting treatment in a non-network
hospital and will
file our claim for reimbursement, then
here we need to keep one important thing in mind
that the non-network hospital should
not be in the blacklist of the company.
Because every company has a blacklist
of network hospitals.
Hospitals where the company does not allow treatment.
After identifying the hospital, the
next step is the type of treatment.
What type of treatment are we going to get
?  There are two types of treatments.
One is plant treatment and the
other is emergency treatment.  Plant
treatment is often done in surgical
procedures where the doctor has
given us a date in advance that
you have to undergo a particular surgery 10 days from today.   The
second is emergency treatment.
Generally, in accidents, in emergency situations, if there is a
sudden attack of dengue, malaria, then
emergency treatment is done here.  There is
no prior planning or preparation.  If we have a treatment plan then the
company offers us a facility that we can
apply for cashless approval from the company in advance.  What is the benefit of this is that on the
day our actual treatment will take place.
Suppose our treatment is on the 15th
and we have applied to the company for cashless approval from the 10th itself.
So when our treatment takes place on the 15th,
we will
not have to spend our time on documentation for approval.  You wo
n't have to wait.  Approval will already be in
place.  So planned treatment is
always advisable.  But when there
is emergency treatment and we
need cashless approval from the company on the spot, then the
company allows that too.  Sometimes
in emergency treatment, it also happens that the hospital
staff may ask you for some advance payment of
₹202.00.  So you do
n't need to worry about this.  This advance
treatment fee that the hospital takes from you, when
your approval comes from the company and when the
final discharge happens, this advance is
refunded to you by the hospital
or it is adjusted in your bill.
So now we come to
step number three of the cashless process.  This
is a very important step because here the
actual claim filing and documentation
work will take place.  First of all, understand that
whether it is our plant surgery treatment or
our emergency treatment.   The
process of cashless documentation is the same in both the cases.  For which you will have to go
to the insurance counter in the hospital,
which is also called TPA counter in colloquial language.
You have to go to this counter and
submit all your documentation.  First of all,
you have to provide four
types of documentation.  You have to
give a copy of your policy.  Number one,
number two your KYC proofs which will include
your Aadhar card, PAN card.  Number
three photographs, one passport size
photograph is required.  End number for
cancelled cheque.  You have to give all these things in the
proposal.  Keep this in mind.  The patient's money is
not to be paid.  If the patient and the proposal are the same then
obviously it doesn't matter.  But if the
proposal in your policy is only
husband proposal then you will have to provide all the documentation of the husband.
After this you will have to fill the pre-authorization
form, which is also called pre-auth form in short.
This is a very important document.
It will contain all the details of your claim.
Starting with your details for
example name, date of birth, address,
mobile number.  After this,
details of the treatment being done, from when to when will the
patient remain admitted?  The
entire estimate will be about how much expense is expected.  And
after this it will contain past medical
history.  If your patient has any
medical history, you will have to provide its details also.
This form is important
because it goes from the hospital
to the insurance company and
sometimes your claim can be rejected on the basis of your past medical history.
So keep in mind that the
pre-authorization form should be
filled by the person who has complete information about your policy
and who knows the entire medical history of your family
so that the company
gets the same information which is in your policy and
they get the same information from the pre-authorization form also.  If there is
any mismatch in it, your claim may get
stuck or even rejected.  Now
we come to step number four of the cashless process.
Here you will get initial
approval.  So when your pre-auth form, all the
documentation, everything is filed by the TK
from the insurance counter to the insurance
company from the hospital, then
after that you will get the initial approval.  This
initial approval will be a partial amount.
For example, if your hospital has
submitted a claim request of ₹1 lakh, you will probably
get an initial approval of ₹30 or ₹25,000.
Which is like an advance.  What it means is
that the insurance company has accepted your claim
and has
sent an advance payment approval to your hospital.
So there is no need to worry here
that you had submitted approval of Rs 1 lakh.
Only ₹00 approval has come from the company.  So
here because this is an age an advance
approval.  As a partial approval.  So now
I come to step number five of the cashless process,
which I call the query step.
This means that your claim has
not been approved.  Rather Insurance Company has
applied a query to the hospital.
He has demanded some document.
So there is no need to panic here also.
The first thing you have to do is
check the query letter because the
company has mentioned its exact requirements in it.
Where will this query letter come?  It will come to your email.
You will receive it on SMS and
also on your company's mobile app.  The
company's requirements in this query letter can be
of two types.  Either
you have to provide those documents or
your hospital or doctor has to provide those documents.
If you have to provide any documents, then
obviously you will have to arrange them
and submit them at the insurance
counter or TPA counter of the hospital so
that those documents can be
submitted to the insurance company.  And
if those documents are to be provided by the hospital or doctor, then
you will have to
intimate your doctor.  You will have to remind them once
so that they can
arrange the documents and
send them to the TPA counter insurance company so that
your claim can go further into the approval process.
Sometimes in the query,
apart from the documents, the company may also
assign investigation in your claim.  In the case where the
investigator visits you, he or she may
also meet with your patient.  He will
obtain information from you about the disease of his claim and may also get some form filled and
signed by you.  Whatever
documents and details you
provide to the investigator, it is preferred
that you keep a copy of it
for future records so that you can use it when needed.
Now we come to the sixth and
last step where we will get the final
approval.  When will I get this?  This will be given at the
time of discharge. When it is
time for discharge of our patient, the
discharge summary and the final bill of the
hospital will be sent by the hospital to the insurance company
and the insurance company will
process it and the final approval will take about two
hours. In this, you can assume that the
insurance company will intimate the hospital as to what
final approval they have given to
your claim.  Keep in mind that the
final approval will come only when the
final medical papers, discharge
summary and final bill have been
sent by the hospital to the insurance company.
Many times it also happens that the doctor has
signed the discharge summary but the
TPA counter has not yet sent the final discharge summary
papers and medical bills
to the insurance company.  So, unless the
file of those documents reaches the insurance company, their processing will
not start.  As soon as the final bill,
discharge summary papers etc. go from the hospital to the
insurance company.  Insurance
Company Most insurance companies send you an
SMS and email informing you that they have
received the final discharge papers.  So
this means you can be confirmed that the
hospital has completed your processing.
So the first situation is that your
claim has been completely approved.
Suppose you had a claim of ₹ lakh, then the
full approval of ₹ lakh has come from the company.
So that means no deduction or
rejection was applied to you.  The second
situation is that some deduction has been
applied to you, suppose your claim was
of ₹ one lakh but the approval from the company was for
₹ 1600, then you can see the complete breakup of the amount of ₹ 400 deducted
in your approval letter (final approval letter), as to
what all has been deducted and if
you have any dispute in it or
you have any counter point in it, then you
can also submit it for review from the insurance company.  And the third situation is that
your claim has been rejected by the company.
So again, you will get the reason for rejection in that letter as to
why it has been rejected.
Again, if you have any dispute in that, if
you have any counter point, then you
can again put it for review
through the insurance counter, through the TPI counter
and if you want, you can
also file your claim for reimbursement later.
To file a reimbursement claim,
you will have to follow the complete process.
For that you can find many videos on our YouTube channel
for reimbursement claim filing.  You can take their help
and file your claim for reimbursement.
So this was our six-step
cashless claim process.  If
you still have any doubt or confusion regarding any point in this, then do
not forget to comment in the comment section.  Stay connected
with Mr. Policy.
Like, share and subscribe for such useful and informative videos.
Thank you for watching.